<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Saad's Blog</title>
 <link href="http://sfarooq.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://sfarooq.github.com"/>
 <updated>2013-07-19T06:55:44-04:00</updated>
 <id>http://sfarooq.github.com</id>
 <author>
   <name>Saad Farooq</name>
   <email>sa@dfarooq.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>CSEd Research Overview</title>
   <link href="http://sfarooq.github.com/research/2013/07/18/csed-research-overview"/>
   <updated>2013-07-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://sfarooq.github.com/research/2013/07/18/csed-research-overview</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id='todos_for_this_week'&gt;Todos for this week&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find keywords for searching for relevant research&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Do a review of reviews&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Find the interesting researchers in the CS education&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id='keywords'&gt;Keywords&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karen Vagts at the Tufts University library provided great insight into searching for articles related to my area of interest which is multidisciplinary and therefore not straight forward to search for good research in. Online databases (like &lt;a href='http://www.eric.ed.gov/'&gt;ERIC&lt;/a&gt; for education) seem to help narrowing down the domain of the search results just by being limited to a certain field. For e.g. searching for functions on Google Scholar returns results from both the mathematical concept of functions as well as the computer science concept of function. ERIC on the other hand only returns results of the math variety. ERIC also provides greater options for filtering the results. Google Scholar is good for general overviews but it seems to make sense to move to a domain specific search provider once you have your topics narrowed down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='keywords_tested'&gt;Keywords Tested&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Survey, overview, taxonomy on ACM&amp;#8217;s SIGCSE website to get the research overview papers&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Searching the computer science category on ERIC In general, Google Scholar does not seem to work too well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id='review_of_reviews'&gt;Review of Reviews&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A survey of literature on the teaching of introductory programming &lt;a href='http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=1345441&amp;amp;CFID=234525748&amp;amp;CFTOKEN=55092647'&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;This much I know: thoughts on the past, present and future of educational programming tools &lt;a href='http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2445196&amp;amp;CFID=234525748&amp;amp;CFTOKEN=55092647'&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Sally Fincher from the University of Kent is a Computer Science Education Researcher Toolkit page &lt;a href='http://www.cs.kent.ac.uk/people/staff/saf/experiment-kits/index.html'&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Usability issues in the Design of Novice Programming System &lt;a href=''&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Not a relevant paper but sounds like a good read ; Reading a computer science research paper &lt;a href='http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=1595493&amp;amp;CFID=234525748&amp;amp;CFTOKEN=55092647'&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Not relevant but ben might like: Survey of test driven development in academia &lt;a href='http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=1383602.1383644&amp;amp;coll=DL&amp;amp;dl=GUIDE&amp;amp;CFID=234525748&amp;amp;CFTOKEN=55092647'&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Just including this because it&amp;#8217;s Mark Guzdial and I should probably know this is the broader picture; A statewide survey on computing education pathways and influences: factors in broadening participation in computing &lt;a href='http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2361276.2361304&amp;amp;coll=DL&amp;amp;dl=GUIDE&amp;amp;CFID=234525748&amp;amp;CFTOKEN=55092647'&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Computational Thinking in K-12: A Review of the State of the Field &lt;a href='http://edr.sagepub.com/content/42/1/38.full.pdf+html?ijkey=yKLHJq4ZYELx.&amp;amp;keytype=ref&amp;amp;siteid=spedr'&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;The future of computer languages; implications for education &lt;a href='http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=5600.5627&amp;amp;coll=DL&amp;amp;dl=GUIDE&amp;amp;CFID=234525748&amp;amp;CFTOKEN=55092647'&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id='researchers'&gt;Researchers&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id='neil_b_dale_university_of_texas'&gt;Neil B Dale, University of Texas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two PhD thesis under here guidance seem pretty relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conceptual Models and Individual Cognitive Learning Styles in Teaching Recursion to Novices, Cheng-Chih Wu, 1993&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Limitations in the Understanding of Mathematical Logic by Novice Computer Science Students,Vicki Lynn Almstrum, 1994.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a paper by her in SIGCSE, title &lt;a href='http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=1138403.1138432&amp;amp;coll=DL&amp;amp;dl=GUIDE&amp;amp;CFID=234525748&amp;amp;CFTOKEN=55092647'&gt;Most difficult topics in CS1: results of an online survey of educators&lt;/a&gt; which sounds really interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='allison_elliot_tew_university_of_washington_tacoma'&gt;Allison Elliot Tew, University of Washington, Tacoma&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Language Independent Assessment of CS1 Scaffolding Research in Computer Science Education Not cognitive enough but better than most CS specific researchers. &lt;a href='http://www.cs.kent.ac.uk/events/conf/2006/icer/icer-talks/2006-icer-guzdial-tew.ppt'&gt;Presentation&lt;/a&gt; from ICER 2006.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='vicki_l_almstrum_utexas_at_austin'&gt;Vicki L. Almstrum, UTexas at Austin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=544414.544471&amp;amp;coll=DL&amp;amp;dl=GUIDE&amp;amp;CFID=234525748&amp;amp;CFTOKEN=55092647'&gt;Import and export to/from computing science education: the case of mathematics education research&lt;/a&gt; I think I&amp;#8217;m in love&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='colin_johnson'&gt;Colin Johnson&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will have to investigate more but he is part of the computer science education group at the University of Kent and his research interests include porting ideas from computing and mathematics to other areas and taking ideas from natural sciences and using them as metaphors for new ways of doing computing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='j_philip_east_northwestern_university'&gt;J Philip East, Northwestern University&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id='janet_kolodoner_georgia_tech'&gt;Janet Kolodoner, Georgia Tech&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id='rosario_vera_ruiz'&gt;Rosario Vera Ruiz&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From IES Jarifa Spain, this researcher published a paper in the &amp;#8216;Internation Journal of Technology in Mathematics Education&amp;#8217; title &amp;#8216;Teaching the Relevance of Mathematics in Information Technology through Functional Programming in Secondary School&amp;#8217;. This sounds exactly in line with the sort of research questions I have. Unfortunately, the remainder of his work appears to be in English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='peter_achten_nijmegen_institute_for_computing_and_information_sciences'&gt;Peter Achten, Nijmegen Institute for Computing and Information Sciences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His primary area of research seems to be functional programming. However, he has an exciting program called &lt;a href='http://www.cs.ru.nl/P.Achten/SoccerFun/SoccerFun.html'&gt;&lt;code&gt;Soccer-Fun&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which is a framework for programming a soccer team using functional languages. The framework is used to teach functional programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='micheal_kolling_university_of_kent'&gt;Micheal Kolling, University of Kent&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BlueJ / Greenfoot author.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='philip_guo_google'&gt;Philip Guo, Google&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not particularly relevant as a CSEd researcher but is pretty active in general HCI and wrote the Online Python Tutor.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>CSTA 2013 Report</title>
   <link href="http://sfarooq.github.com/research/2013/07/16/csta-2013-report"/>
   <updated>2013-07-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://sfarooq.github.com/research/2013/07/16/csta-2013-report</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id='general_overview'&gt;General Overview&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference, as the title would suggest is geared towards teachers of Computer Science, particularly at the school level. The sessions therefore, were based more on the practical elements of teaching computer science than theoretical understanding of Computer Science concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id='programming_through_art_and_math_sheena_vaidyanathan'&gt;Programming through Art and Math: Sheena Vaidyanathan&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sheena Vaidyanathan runs a program called &lt;a href='http://www.computersforcreativity.com/school-programs/lasdcstem'&gt;CSTEM&lt;/a&gt; in the Los Altos school districts of California. The stated program highlights are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pair Programming&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Focus on design, art, creativity&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Extensive use of Edmodo to engage and assign work, post finished projects, comment on posts, ask questions after class, homework/quizzes, class discussions&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Student showcase and competition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talk was mostly about her use of Processing.js via &lt;a href='http://www.khanacademy.org/cs'&gt;KhanAcademy.org&lt;/a&gt; to engage students in programming through art. She also advocated &lt;a href='http://www.edmodo.com'&gt;Edmodo&lt;/a&gt; as a communications tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her website &lt;a href='http://www.computersforcreativity.com/'&gt;www.computersforcreativity.com&lt;/a&gt; details this and her other endeavors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='my_notes'&gt;My Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was intrigued by this session because of the mention of art, math and programming and the possibility of the use of math and arts education and learning science to influence computer science learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My impression though, is that the role of programming is unclear. I haven&amp;#8217;t read any of Sheena&amp;#8217;s other work so I may be wrong but the talk seemed to be more about the usability of tools rather than it&amp;#8217;s effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She did however, mention that introducing kids to Processing&amp;#8217;s text based setup before Scratch led to some struggles with syntax but ultimately some kids preferred it to the drag-and-drop of Scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id='computer_science_with_calico_douglas_blank_laura_blankenship_ashley_gavin_jim_marshall_jennifer_s_kay_keith_ohara_mark_f_russo'&gt;Computer Science with Calico: Douglas Blank, Laura Blankenship, Ashley Gavin, Jim Marshall, Jennifer S. Kay, Keith O’Hara, Mark F. Russo&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://calicoproject.org/'&gt;Calico&lt;/a&gt; is a multi-language programming environment/IDE. Right now it has the following languages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jigsaw (a Scratch like drag and drop)&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Python&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Scheme&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system is designed around transitions from (Scratch -&amp;gt; Jigsaw -&amp;gt; Python -&amp;gt; Scheme) but they aren&amp;#8217;t limiting themselves to just these languages. Java is coming up and they have plans for other languages too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They weren&amp;#8217;t able to go through the whole presentation but it&amp;#8217;s shared online (&lt;a href='http://goo.gl/p2oKk'&gt;http://goo.gl/p2oKk&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system seems very professionally made and has some great features built-in. Some of which are :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A shell within the IDE&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Simulator for robots so you don&amp;#8217;t need an actual physical robot for testing (they showed off the Scribbler bot)&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Real-time display of all the robot&amp;#8217;s (/simulated robot) parameters&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;ROS module for communicating with ROS enabled robots&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;All languages in a similar enivornment so the cognitive load of learning a new environment is spared&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id='my_notes'&gt;My Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the most interesting of the talks that I saw. There was some chaos around live demos but overall the demos were pretty cool and displayed the versatility of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be really awesome if the system could make libraries in one language could be made available in other languages. Don&amp;#8217;t know how hard that would be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id='inspiring_high_school_students_in_stem_using_app_inventor_kristin_violette_and_shaileen_pokress'&gt;Inspiring High School Students in STEM Using App Inventor: Kristin Violette and Shaileen Pokress&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This session was more an account of how MIT AppInventor was used in a class-room in Connecticut and representatives of the class eventually ended up winning a state wide competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not a lot was mentioned about the software except for an (informal) announcement that the Alpha of the latest version of AppInventor was just released at &lt;a href='http://ai2.appinventor.mit.edu/'&gt;http://ai2.appinventor.mit.edu/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='my_notes'&gt;My Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This session was more oriented towards teachers that want to use AppInventor in their classrooms. One thing that I did find interesting about the implementation that the teacher was using was that they used a business oriented format i.e. the students made an elevator pitch about their apps that was &amp;#8220;judged&amp;#8221; by a &lt;code&gt;Shark Tank&lt;/code&gt; like panel. Even though it&amp;#8217;s not really my area of research, I imagine there are some interesting links between student&amp;#8217;s engagement and the popularity of &amp;#8216;Shark Tank&amp;#8217;, the television show. That would be a good social psychology question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id='mobile_programming_throwdown__david_reed_moderator_alfred_thompson_windows_ralph_morelli_android_and_xxx_ios'&gt;Mobile Programming Throwdown : David Reed (Moderator), Alfred Thompson (Windows), Ralph Morelli (Android), and XXX (iOS)&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First done at last year&amp;#8217;s conference, experts on the three main mobile development platforms Apple iOS, Google Android and Microsoft Windows Phone were give a task of developing a simple app live. The people came pre-prepared though so they could copy and paste pre-prepared snippets into the code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app idea this year was an app that looks through the phone contacts and randomly shows a contact with the ability to place a call to that contact. Kind of a &lt;code&gt;&amp;#39;I&amp;#39;m feeling lucky&amp;#39; for phone calls&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each platform had approximately 15 minutes to build their app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='my_notes'&gt;My Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, Windows Phone was the cleanest and quickest of the three platforms. I&amp;#8217;m never been a fan of how Visual Studio adds so much annoying infrastructure to the system instead of just starting barebones but for once, I was made to eat my words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apple was by far the worst, the code was hard to follow along with and things were going on all over the place. The developer who already has a well known app on the AppStore couldn&amp;#8217;t finish in the alloted 15 minutes. The Android developer used MIT AppInventor for most of the work. However, since AppInventor is a much higher level abstraction, it didn&amp;#8217;t have the necessary feature for the random contact selection to be done entirely in AppInventor. For that part, the programmer used standard Java and referenced that from AppInventor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AppInventor doesn&amp;#8217;t give the whole feel of the Android Java system but since I have experience in that domain I can say that Windows Phone was still the clearest and easiet of the three systems.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Android Gradle Project Management</title>
   <link href="http://sfarooq.github.com/development/2013/07/12/android-gradle-project-management"/>
   <updated>2013-07-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://sfarooq.github.com/development/2013/07/12/android-gradle-project-management</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id='basic_gradle_setup'&gt;Basic Gradle Setup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google decided to use Gradle is the build tool for Android recently and duely integrated the Gradle build system with Android Studio, the new IntelliJ IDEA based IDE. There is some great documentation about the new build system on &lt;a href='http://tools.android.com/tech-docs/new-build-system/user-guide'&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Specifications for Online Educational and Robotics Platform</title>
   <link href="http://sfarooq.github.com/2013/07/11/specifications-for-online-educational-and-robotics-platform"/>
   <updated>2013-07-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://sfarooq.github.com/2013/07/11/specifications-for-online-educational-and-robotics-platform</id>
   <content type="html"></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Review of Research Articles on Kids' Understanding of Functions</title>
   <link href="http://sfarooq.github.com/research/2013/07/10/review-of-research-articles-on-kids-understanding-of-functions"/>
   <updated>2013-07-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://sfarooq.github.com/research/2013/07/10/review-of-research-articles-on-kids-understanding-of-functions</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id='main_ideas'&gt;Main Ideas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id='process_view_of_functions'&gt;Process View of Functions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students need to be able to see functions as a process rather than a mapping of a discrete input value to a discrete output value. The process view of functions is a way to look at functions as something of a &amp;#8220;black box&amp;#8221; which performs a process on a &amp;#8216;set&amp;#8217; of input values rather than discrete input values. As opposed to the &amp;#8220;action view&amp;#8221; of functions in which some action is performed, e.g. substitution of values in an equation and a static output is achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='covariational_reasoning'&gt;Covariational Reasoning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Covariational reasoning is the understanding of changes in input mapping to changes in output i.e. the covariation of outputs with inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='research_questions'&gt;Research Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do students in introductory computer science / programming courses having similar struggles with programming procedures (alternate term for functions to avoid confusion)?&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Is the representation of functions in computer programming an abstraction from the mathematical view of functions that is helpful in articulating the borders between&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id='todos_for_next_week'&gt;To-Dos For Next Week&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find keywords for searching for relevant research&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Do a review of reviews&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Find the interesting researchers in the CS education&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Loading Excel Files in Yii</title>
   <link href="http://sfarooq.github.com/development/2013/07/08/loading-excel-files-in-yii"/>
   <updated>2013-07-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://sfarooq.github.com/development/2013/07/08/loading-excel-files-in-yii</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id='library_to_use'&gt;Library to Use&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://phpexcel.codeplex.com/'&gt;PHPExcel&lt;/a&gt; is the most comprehensive Excel manipulation library for PHP. I has great features for reading and manipulating Excel (and related) files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a number of extensions written for Yii that claim to work. I didn&amp;#8217;t think any of them gave the complete array of features and some were just using PHPExcel in the background anyway.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Custom Android Builds with Gradle</title>
   <link href="http://sfarooq.github.com/2013/07/01/custom-android-builds-with-gradle"/>
   <updated>2013-07-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://sfarooq.github.com/2013/07/01/custom-android-builds-with-gradle</id>
   <content type="html"></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>POST request from AngularJS with Yii</title>
   <link href="http://sfarooq.github.com/development/2013/06/29/post-request-from-angularjs-with-yii"/>
   <updated>2013-06-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://sfarooq.github.com/development/2013/06/29/post-request-from-angularjs-with-yii</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t like Yii much. Maybe it&amp;#8217;s cause of the overbloatedness of PHP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AngularJS, which is what I&amp;#8217;m using in the front-end, allows you to send Javascript objects using POST requests via JSON. When you do that, you expect there to be a &lt;code&gt;$_POST&lt;/code&gt; object in Yii from which you can conveniently partake of your desired data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After spending some time trying to figure out why that is so, I came upon &lt;a href='http://learnyii.blogspot.com/2011/11/yii-json-post-model-save.html'&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; post. It&amp;#8217;s annoying but basically you have to just do a low-level PHP read using.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='highlight'&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class='php'&gt;&lt;span class='x'&gt;$post = file_get_contents(&amp;quot;php://input&amp;quot;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh Yii !! How I hate thee&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Image/Thumbnail Gallery with AngularJS</title>
   <link href="http://sfarooq.github.com/development/2013/06/27/imagethumbnail-gallery-with-angularjs"/>
   <updated>2013-06-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://sfarooq.github.com/development/2013/06/27/imagethumbnail-gallery-with-angularjs</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I need to add a thumbnail gallery for the reports we provide on our online platform. Twitter Bootstrap has a great framework for setting this up quite easily using available CSS classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, I&amp;#8217;m just going to use the default setup and use CSS3 animations to fade in and out the images based on what&amp;#8217;s being hovered over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what it looks like right now:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='highlight'&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class='css'&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nt'&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;row-fluid&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nt'&gt;ng-controller&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;ThumbnailsCtrl&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;ul&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nt'&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;thumbnails&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;li&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nt'&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;span4&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nt'&gt;ng-repeat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;report in reports&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nt'&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;thumbnail&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;img&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nt'&gt;data-src&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;holder.js/300x200&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nt'&gt;alt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;300x200&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nt'&gt;style&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;width: 300px; height: 200px;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nt'&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                        &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;h3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;h3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                        &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                        &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nt'&gt;href&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;#&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nt'&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;btn btn-primary&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;Go&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nt'&gt;To&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nt'&gt;Report&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;div&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;div&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;li&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;ul&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;div&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Server Side Pagination with ngTable</title>
   <link href="http://sfarooq.github.com/development/2013/06/26/server-side-pagination-with-ngtable"/>
   <updated>2013-06-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://sfarooq.github.com/development/2013/06/26/server-side-pagination-with-ngtable</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id='what_is_server_side_pagination'&gt;What is Server Side Pagination?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you just have too much data to fit comfortably on a single page of a table or data-grid. There are two ways to deal with this. Client side pagination is when you get all the data from the server and use Javascript to show only some of it on the one page. Upon navigation to a different page, a new set of data is loaded. In server side pagination, only the amount of data to be shown on one page is loaded from the server. Upon navigation to a different page a new call is made to the server to get data for that page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='server_side_pagination_with_ngtable'&gt;Server Side Pagination with ngTable&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose ngTable as my standard table view. The reasons for this choice are detailed &lt;a href='2013-06-23-data-grids-with-angularjs.html'&gt;elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='getting_totals'&gt;Getting Totals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As explained &lt;a href='http://www.arraystudio.com/as-workshop/mysql-get-total-number-of-rows-when-using-limit.html'&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; getting the total values that &amp;#8220;would&amp;#8221; be returned is absolutely essential if you are going to have pagination.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Integrating Yii with Twitter Bootstrap</title>
   <link href="http://sfarooq.github.com/development/2013/06/24/integrating-yii-with-twitter-bootstrap"/>
   <updated>2013-06-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://sfarooq.github.com/development/2013/06/24/integrating-yii-with-twitter-bootstrap</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id='why_twitter_boostrap'&gt;Why Twitter Boostrap?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to include &lt;a href='http://twitter.github.com/bootstrap'&gt;Twitter Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt;. The primary reason for doing so if to get the &lt;a href='http://twitter.github.io/bootstrap/scaffolding.html#gridSystem'&gt;grid&lt;/a&gt; capability which is just way more convenient that setting weird CSS on elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='options'&gt;Options&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There seem to be two ways to do this. One is using Yii&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href='http://www.cniska.net/yii-bootstrap/'&gt;Twitter Bootstrap extension&lt;/a&gt;. Using this extension you would add Twitter components to your page using snippets like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='highlight'&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class='php'&gt;&lt;span class='cp'&gt;&amp;lt;?php&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nv'&gt;$this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='na'&gt;widget&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;bootstrap.widgets.TbButton&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;array&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;label&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;Primary&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;type&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;primary&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='c1'&gt;// null, &amp;#39;primary&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;info&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;success&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;warning&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;danger&amp;#39; or &amp;#39;inverse&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;size&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;large&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='c1'&gt;// null, &amp;#39;large&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;small&amp;#39; or &amp;#39;mini&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='p'&gt;));&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='cp'&gt;?&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='x' /&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As opposed to :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='highlight'&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class='html'&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;button&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;btn btn-primary&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Button&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/button&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that settles it. I&amp;#8217;m going to go for the latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='how_to_use_it'&gt;How To Use It&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yii supports layout inheritance. You can define layouts at the Application, Controller or View level. Since, I&amp;#8217;m going to be using the same layout throughout the views I&amp;#8217;ll be setting it up at the Controller level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I create a new file called &lt;code&gt;twitter-bootstrap.php&lt;/code&gt; in the &lt;code&gt;views/layouts&lt;/code&gt; folder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='highlight'&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class='php'&gt;&lt;span class='x'&gt;class DashboardController extends Controller&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='x'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='x'&gt;    public $layout=&amp;#39;//layouts/twitter-bootstrap&amp;#39;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='x'&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simple. All views of this controller will now use the layout defined in &lt;code&gt;twitter-bootstrap.php&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='now_the_hard_part'&gt;Now the Hard Part&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to define the layout itself ? Should be simple enough:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='highlight'&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class='html'&gt;&lt;span class='cp'&gt;&amp;lt;!DOCTYPE html&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='cp'&gt;&amp;lt;?php echo CHtml::cssFile(Yii::app()-&amp;gt;baseUrl.&amp;#39;/css/bootstrap.css&amp;#39;); ?&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;container-fluid&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;row-fluid&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;id=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;header&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            ...site logo and other header content...
        &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class='cp'&gt;&amp;lt;?php echo $content; ?&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;row-fluid&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;id=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;footer&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        ...footer content...
    &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='c'&gt;&amp;lt;!-- footer --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='c'&gt;&amp;lt;!-- container --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Integrating Yeoman based Project with Yii</title>
   <link href="http://sfarooq.github.com/development/2013/06/23/integrating-yeoman-create-project-with-yii"/>
   <updated>2013-06-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://sfarooq.github.com/development/2013/06/23/integrating-yeoman-create-project-with-yii</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id='options'&gt;Options&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Yeoman based Angular project builds to HTML and Javascript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two main options for integrating with Yii.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Static HTML served directly from a directory&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;HTML injected into a Yii PHP view&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id='static_html'&gt;Static HTML&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Yeoman project is enclosed in a self enclosed directory named &lt;code&gt;app&lt;/code&gt; during development and builds to a &lt;code&gt;dist&lt;/code&gt; directory. All required HTML and CSS files are within the same directory. The Angular framework has a level of abstraction implemented via directives called &lt;code&gt;ng-app&lt;/code&gt;. Each &lt;code&gt;ng-app&lt;/code&gt; contains multiple controllers (via &lt;code&gt;ng-controller&lt;/code&gt;) which are data bound with associated &lt;code&gt;Controller&lt;/code&gt; functions in Javascript. Routing can be implemented at the &lt;code&gt;ng-app&lt;/code&gt; level with URL routes of the &lt;code&gt;#/&amp;lt;route&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; pattern being assigned to various subviews by the Angular framework. This provides a nice modulization of Javascript actions and DOM manipulation (something which is particularly annoying otherwise) and also allows for bookmarkable URLs. E.g. the view&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;http://localhost/#/firstview
http://localhost/#/secondview&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;can be implemented using different HTML files via the Angular routing mechanism. And be assigned to different &lt;code&gt;ng-controllers&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='implementation'&gt;Implementation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implementation in conjunction with Yii turns out to be simple. Copying the &lt;code&gt;app&lt;/code&gt; (or &lt;code&gt;dist&lt;/code&gt;) folder to the root of the Yii server creates the URL which simply loads the static HTML app. No problems at all. The Yii framework in the default configuration only routes the URL portion beyond the &lt;code&gt;/index.php/&lt;/code&gt; to a Yii controller. Following are the two URL patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;http://&amp;lt;serverroot&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;angular-app-directory&amp;gt;/
http://&amp;lt;serverroot&amp;gt;/index.php/&amp;lt;controller&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;action&amp;gt;/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Angular static HTML in conjuction with Yii simply works using the former URL scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='as_a_yii_view'&gt;As a Yii View&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yii views are rendered as PHP files. The parser parses any PHP directives in the view files, but only if there are any (smirks). By copying the contents of the Angular app&amp;#8217;s HTML file to a PHP view file, it is simply rendered as HTML. The only problem now is making sure that the script loading tags work as expected. This turns out to be not so simple using just strings. The paths have to be hard-coded because Yii does not allow access to relative paths in sub-directories. Futhermore, the HTML files that make up the modularized views routed by the Angular app via URL routes must also be served as static files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='implementation'&gt;Implementation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the static files are served via hard-coded paths. Once a decision is reached on what pattern of development to follow, the scripts and stylesheets are best served via the Yii assets system. This system takes scripts / stylesheet URLs from a standard directory and serves them via relative paths built during the compile process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='layout_inheritance'&gt;Layout Inheritance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of this writing, the Angular app served the Yii view inherits some layout from the default Yii layout whereas some is derived from the HTML app. This results in some disarray in the overall layout. The feed column which is designed to take up about a quarter of the real estate is limited to just enough to hold the placeholder text. Updating the script loading as above and abstracing the common elements to a Yii layout should fix this problem pleasantly based on the decision on what method to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='trailing_issues'&gt;Trailing Issues&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only remaining matter is the serving of the static HTML sub-view files. I&amp;#8217;ll need to investigate some more on this. Perhaps Yii offers a way to serve these similar to how scripts are served. In the case where that is not possible, some security review might be undertaken of the situation. It is all just HTML and JS and not data is actually used until the app is running and the server authorizes the data, but you never know.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Data Grids with AngularJS</title>
   <link href="http://sfarooq.github.com/development/2013/06/23/data-grids-with-angularjs"/>
   <updated>2013-06-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://sfarooq.github.com/development/2013/06/23/data-grids-with-angularjs</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id='criteria'&gt;Criteria&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, lets start with we want in our data grids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frontend (JS) driven - with all the tweaking that is expected of tables / grids, working from JS is just simpler instead of doing some processing in one language and some in another. I&amp;#8217;ve run into problems using multiple languages previously where SQL was not flexible enough to do good processing of data. I then had to do some processing in a server side language (PHP) and some in the frontend using Javascript. This approach is way easier, just get the raw unformatted data from SQL and do everything in Javascript.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Flexible - there is a tradeoff here. On the one hand, it would be good to have control over individual columns. On the other, it might be convenient to just give a widget data and have it show up.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Easy to manipulate - similar to flexible above, some of the problems with the Yii plugin we previously used is it was too rigid. You could only used the options that they already have built-in and it&amp;#8217;s not very declarative.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id='options'&gt;Options&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using native Angular directives&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Using a pre-built Data-grid&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id='native_angular'&gt;Native Angular&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angular directives give a great way to roll your own table using whatever data-types you prefer. The implementation of the table in the current layout is just the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='highlight'&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class='html'&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;table&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;thead&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;tr&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;th&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;ng-repeat=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;header in headers&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;  {{ header }} &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/th&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/thead&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;tbody&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;tr&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;ng-repeat=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;value in values | filter:filterBy&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;td&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;  {{ value.Title }}        &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;td&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;  {{ value.Description }}  &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;td&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;  {{ value.Date }}         &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;td&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;  {{ value.Password }}     &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/tbody&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/table&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But where does the data come from. Well, in the controller you just use Angular&amp;#8217;s &lt;code&gt;$http&lt;/code&gt; service to make a web call and set the returned value to a variable on the scope. The data-binding guarantees that the data shows up on the same variable in the HTML.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='highlight'&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class='js'&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;$http&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;({&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;method&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;GET&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;url&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;http://someserver&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;}).&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='nx'&gt;success&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='kd'&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;status&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;headers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;config&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='nx'&gt;$scope&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;headers&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nb'&gt;Object&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;keys&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='mi'&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;]);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='c1'&gt;// get the headers from one row&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='nx'&gt;$scope&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;values&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='p'&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And voila, the data fills up the table. Also, notice the filter &amp;#8220;piped&amp;#8221; after the &lt;code&gt;ng-repeat&lt;/code&gt; directive. By simply adding:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='highlight'&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class='html'&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;input&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;ng-model=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;filterBy&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/input&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;to the page, the table is filtered by the values containing the string from input. No other code necessary. Isn&amp;#8217;t that cool&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, we can also write other filters. In our application, filtering is a great tool because of the large lists we have. That coupled with the fact that I&amp;#8217;ve never liked the look of data-grid (they seem too&amp;#8230; serious) so this option is definitely my favorite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='using_a_prebuilt_datagrid'&gt;Using a Pre-Built Data-grid&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, there are plenty of options to choose from. I couldn&amp;#8217;t get the ones I tried to work out of the box and it turned out it might have to do with setting some data before the HTTP call is made and then updating the data instead of setting it just on the success callback (now called promise).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, the one I&amp;#8217;m using is called &lt;a href='http://angular-ui.github.io/ng-grid/'&gt;ng-grid&lt;/a&gt;. The only problem you need to be aware of with this (apart from the setting data as above) is that initially it might only show a couple rows of data. Turns out it&amp;#8217;s a bug in Javascript. There is a workaround suggested &lt;a href='https://github.com/angular-ui/ng-grid/issues/80'&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to make sure it uses &lt;code&gt;auto&lt;/code&gt; height until the bug is fixed but it didn&amp;#8217;t work for me so I had to set the height manually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others that might be of interest are : &lt;a href='http://lorenzofox3.github.io/smart-table-website/'&gt;Smart Table&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href='http://angulartable.com/'&gt;Angular Table&lt;/a&gt;. Angular Table claims to be completely declarative which is cool. Unfortunately, I couldn&amp;#8217;t get it to work right in the limited time I had. Might have to give it another try soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='conclusion'&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;d love to just go with the native Angular table but I realize that might be too geeky overall. Will have to see what the group decides. Might just end up doing it with Yii in the end.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>In Search of a Front End Development Framework</title>
   <link href="http://sfarooq.github.com/development/2013/06/16/in-search-of-a-front-end-development-framework"/>
   <updated>2013-06-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://sfarooq.github.com/development/2013/06/16/in-search-of-a-front-end-development-framework</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id='frontend_development_framework'&gt;Front-end Development Framework&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As bad as it is, Javascript is here to stay and server side development still doesn&amp;#8217;t help get rid of it (and introduces plenty of problems of it&amp;#8217;s own). So if we&amp;#8217;re in this mess, might as well try to make it a little less gross. Many have tried (and continue to try) to make web app development less painful. We&amp;#8217;re giving one of our projects a makeover so I though I might as well try to find a new framework that works better than our current setup (PHP Yii, arghh).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='criteria'&gt;Criteria&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main criteria that I want in the new framework:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decoupling Server and Client - the framework should be frontend driven i.e. the front end is a Javascript based client app and the backend is comprised of RESTFul web services. The separation gives us some separation of concerns and makes extending the platform to use mobile based clients easier.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Support for testing - I suck at testing. I write stuff and assume it&amp;#8217;s true for the completely plausible reason that I wrote it. I was introduced to the &lt;code&gt;Test Driven Development&lt;/code&gt; philosophy recently and I totally buy into it. So I would like to have support for testing in the framework.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Support for modularization - I don&amp;#8217;t think I can get this is Javascript. In fact, this should be on the list. It should be a given but since we are working with Javascript, this will probably only remain on the list and never see fruition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from that, I wouldn&amp;#8217;t mind these features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Package Management&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Dependency Management&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Scaffolding&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Bootstrapping that&amp;#8217;s close to what I&amp;#8217;m looking for&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id='introducing_yeoman'&gt;Introducing Yeoman&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went over a lot of stuff over the past few days and &lt;a href='http://www.yeoman.io'&gt;Yeoman&lt;/a&gt; seems to be the way to go. The &lt;code&gt;1.0&lt;/code&gt; version of Yeoman aims at bringing existing tools together instead of trying to do everything itself. It seems to try to mimic a &lt;code&gt;Rails&lt;/code&gt; type system. &lt;code&gt;Grunt&lt;/code&gt; is the build tool and &lt;code&gt;Bower&lt;/code&gt; is the package/dependency manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yoeman includes a tool called &lt;code&gt;Yo&lt;/code&gt;. It also has a variety of generators that can be used to scaffold apps. They seem to work pretty great out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='current_status'&gt;Current Status&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The generators I&amp;#8217;m currently exploring are &lt;code&gt;generator-webapp&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;generator-angular&lt;/code&gt;. The testing framework for the &lt;code&gt;webapp&lt;/code&gt; generator is &lt;a href='http://visionmedia.github.io/mocha/'&gt;Mocha&lt;/a&gt; and it uses &lt;a href='http://chaijs.com/'&gt;ChaiJS&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href='https://github.com/LearnBoost/expect.js/'&gt;ExpectJS&lt;/a&gt; for assertion (I don&amp;#8217;t know why, it&amp;#8217;s kinda weird). The &lt;a href='http://angularjs.org/'&gt;AngularJS&lt;/a&gt; generator uses &lt;a href='http://karma-runner.github.io/0.8/index.html'&gt;Karma&lt;/a&gt; as their testing framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='what_now_'&gt;What now ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;#8217;t tested the two options enough yet, but I feel like Angular has more momentum and it&amp;#8217;s easier to get starting using TDD with Angular just because they have more documentation available. I tried Mocha + Chai + Expect but kept getting lost with who&amp;#8217;s doing what so it&amp;#8217;s higly probably that I&amp;#8217;m gonna go with Angular via Yeoman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='extras'&gt;Extras&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a video on getting starting the Yeoman by Addy Osmani from Google.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Research Proposal I</title>
   <link href="http://sfarooq.github.com/research/2013/06/12/research-proposal-i"/>
   <updated>2013-06-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://sfarooq.github.com/research/2013/06/12/research-proposal-i</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id='research_study_proposal__fall_2013'&gt;Research Study Proposal - Fall 2013&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This document aims to formulate a research study proposal related to research in the area of computer science education. The basic idea is to introduce computer science principles, particularly those related to programming; and especially functional programming, to students in K-12 by using mathematics as a lauchpad for their foray into computer science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposal bases itself on a number of reasonable assumptions that are influence by discussions and things picked up here andt here . However, the absense of citations for these is obvious at this point and will hopefully be filled in over time via references to previous (or our own) research backing those claims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research evolves into two distinct research questions :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can student work to understand the complex concepts of mathematics be leveraged to cause a &amp;#8216;transfer of training effect&amp;#8217; towards computer science (and vice versa) ?&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Can notation be used as a &amp;#8216;tool of thought&amp;#8217; to ease the transfer of concepts from mathematics to functional programming ?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will elaborate on each of these in turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='functional_math'&gt;Functional Math&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Functional programming derives heavily from lambda calculus; a form of calculus that was conceived long before computers were the norm, for expressing mathematical computation. The influence of lambda calculus on functional programming gives it very strong mathematical roots. However, in spite of their obvious overlaps, neither field seems to augment the other in education. Students work their way through hard mathematical concepts and very little of that hard work is carried over to the programming realm &lt;span&gt;citation needed&lt;/span&gt;. The hypothesis that the study would aim to affirm is that both fields are very similar but it is the pedagogical treatment of the concepts that makes the transfer difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I propose a study that asks people of various age groups what they thought were the hardest concepts were in mathematics and compares it to the same question asked of computer science students with reference to programming. The intuition is that both groups will find the concept of &amp;#8216;function as data&amp;#8217; to be among the hardest concepts. In mathematics, this concept is exhibited by operations such as derivative, summations, transforms, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rationale here is that mathematics education does not elaborate the &amp;#8216;function as data&amp;#8217; concept explicitly and by coming up with pedagogical strategies to do so, we can make comp105 much less painful for future students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='particulars_of_study'&gt;Particulars of Study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be decided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='notation_as_a_tool_of_thought'&gt;Notation as a Tool of Thought&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kenneth_E._Iverson'&gt;Kenneth Iverson&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8217;s work on the use of mathematical notation in computer programming earned him a Turing award and led to the development of the APL programming language. &amp;#8216;Notation as a Tool of Thought&amp;#8217; was the title of his Turing award lecture. As the title suggests, it implies the utility of notation in the thought process. He came up with a notation called a the &amp;#8216;Iverson notation&amp;#8217; which could be used for writing and rationalizing about computer programs without being on a computer and the same notation could be transferred to the computer and just run &lt;span&gt;citation needed&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notation seems to form another barrier to the &amp;#8216;transfer of training&amp;#8217; from mathematics to computer programming. In computer science courses, students find it hard to translate notational rules into computer programs &lt;span&gt;citation needed&lt;/span&gt; and whereas the Iverson notation gave a way to unite the two worlds, the effect of the differences in notation was never formalized in research &lt;span&gt;citation needed&lt;/span&gt;. Furthermore, the Iverson notation itself is a complex, hard to understand notation that was limited to using symbols that could be made available at the time &lt;span&gt;citation needed, seems a weird claim&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more intuitive notation system, coupled with the versatility of input systems today could help in bridging the gap between notational mathematics and computer programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research study in this case is more an investigative study (would help if I knew more about research methodologies). We go in with no assumptions or hypotheses and give the subjects the task of coming up with concise notations for particular notational scenarios (possibly inspired by the first study above) and look for patterns in the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='particulars_of_study'&gt;Particulars of Study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be decided.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Changing Minds by Andrea Di Sessa</title>
   <link href="http://sfarooq.github.com/reviews/2013/06/12/changing-minds-by-andrea-di-sessa"/>
   <updated>2013-06-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://sfarooq.github.com/reviews/2013/06/12/changing-minds-by-andrea-di-sessa</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id='introduction'&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is about the significant points and arguments I found in Andrea diSessa&amp;#8217;s book &lt;code&gt;Changing
Minds&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='things_for_meeting'&gt;Things for Meeting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discuss the comparison of computational literacy hierarchy with other literacy hierarchy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computational literacy is unique in that the content created is consumed in a different way i.e. With language literacy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Literary actions: reading / writing&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Creation action : writing&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Consumption action : reading With computation literacy&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Literary actions: reading / writing code&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Creation: write &amp;#8220;code&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Consumption: read &amp;#8220;code&amp;#8221; / consume application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More like scientific literacy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you pay for my CSTA-13 registration ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The World of Functions as a Function&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Designing event based languages on the argument that they are more intuivitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id='research_questions'&gt;Research Questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is teaching the &amp;#8220;everything is a function philosophy&amp;#8221; worth it ?&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;How much harder is it in comparison ?&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Can it be a literacy extendable to arts who don&amp;#8217;t necessarily understand that they are doing math?&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;What do kids instinctively know, what can be elaborated on to make it clear and what has to be taught anew ?&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Can this philosophy be compatible with state based computational approaches? for e.g. programming a robot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id='notes'&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The tick model provides a good analogy to calculus i.e. looking at unit step intervals that make up a larger process (process is not the correct word)&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Lambda calculus provides a better mapping to algebra in my opinion.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;The notational significance of the &lt;em&gt;dx/dy&lt;/em&gt; notation vs Newton&amp;#8217;s notation is emphasized. Seems to the be the most common example.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Scientific communities are tool-rich cultures. Education does not seem to be.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Algebra, calculus, tables are representational tools.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Tools are abandoned as better tools come to forth.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Tools in schoool tend be an end in thomselves and are related to outcomes like &amp;#8220;doing well in school&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Need to understand &lt;em&gt;p-prims&lt;/em&gt; better.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Half a literacy is not enough&lt;/em&gt; to be revisited&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id='likes'&gt;Likes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The idea of teachers creating content is great&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;p-prim&lt;/em&gt; : &lt;em&gt;phenomenological primitives&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id='books_to_read'&gt;Books to Read:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How People Learn&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Turtle Geometry&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Mindstorms&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Windows on Mathematical Learning - Richard Noss and Celia Hoile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id='reading'&gt;Reading:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Three papers on young people&amp;#8217;s learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Starting on Git</title>
   <link href="http://sfarooq.github.com/development/2013/05/03/starting-on-git"/>
   <updated>2013-05-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://sfarooq.github.com/development/2013/05/03/starting-on-git</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id='getting_started_with_git'&gt;Getting started with Git&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id='assumptions'&gt;Assumptions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You know what version control is&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;You know how to install software on whatever platform you are using&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;You know how to set PATH environments etc. if you can&amp;#8217;t get &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; to respond on your command line&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id='where_we_start'&gt;Where we start&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go to your console and do the following&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  $ git --version 
  git version 1.7.9&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don&amp;#8217;t get that something went wrong and you need to figure out how to get &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; on your path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='initializing_your_repo'&gt;Initializing your repo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; repository is basically like a directory that is mirrored somewhere on a server. To initialize a directory as a &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; repository, do :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ mkdir test 
$ cd test 
$ git init 
Initialized empty Git repository in /home/Saad/workspace/test/.git/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice the &lt;code&gt;.git&lt;/code&gt; at the end there. That&amp;#8217;s where all the settings are kept. Once you are a master guru of this stuff, you might actually end up editing config files in the directory to change stuff. In the mean time, it is sufficient to know that this is what defines the repository. If you delete this, your repo becomes a normal directory again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='setting_up_remotes'&gt;Setting up remotes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that you have a local repository, you may want to connect it to a &amp;#8216;remote&amp;#8217; &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; server like &lt;a href='http://www.bitbucket.org'&gt;Bitbucket&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href='http://www.github.com'&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. These are called your &lt;code&gt;remotes&lt;/code&gt; and, understandably, all the manipulation of the remotes is done using the &lt;code&gt;git
remote&lt;/code&gt; series of commands. Once you make a repo on either Github or Bitbucket, it will have a URL. This will either be in HTTP form (&lt;em&gt;https://&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;) or SSH form (&lt;em&gt;git@github.com:&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;). You can look up how to set up your SSH key on the server if you want to use the SSH form URL. Once you have this URL, from your local &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; repo do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ git remote add origin ssh://git@bitbucket.org/saadfarooq/test.git&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this should tell you that you can more than one remote to a single repository. It&amp;#8217;s convention to call the remote as &lt;em&gt;origin&lt;/em&gt;. So now your local repository is connected to the remote repository &lt;em&gt;origin&lt;/em&gt;. Good work !&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='branches'&gt;Branches&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other important concept here is branching. Consider that you and your friend are working on your research project. You friend comes up with this wonderful idea to so something clever but you don&amp;#8217;t quit trust it and don&amp;#8217;t want him to be messing with your code until you are sure that it works (this isn&amp;#8217;t the only possible scenario of course). What do you do ? That&amp;#8217;s where branching comes in. Branching allowing you to take pick up on progress at a particular point and start from that snapshot of code onwards in some other direction. Of course they can be &amp;#8220;merged&amp;#8221; later but we&amp;#8217;ll get to that. All you really need to know about branching at this point is that when you start a repo, it is always on branch &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='staging_changes'&gt;Staging changes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now for the real stuff. So the reason we have the version control system is to save changes. &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; is different from &lt;code&gt;subversion&lt;/code&gt; in that it has two levels of staging i.e. you &amp;#8220;commit&amp;#8221; you changes to the local repository before &amp;#8220;push&amp;#8221;ing them to the remote repo. That is a concept you should grasp well. What this means is that you could have just the local repository and have it track your changes without connecting it to the remote repo at all. The local repository is essentially the same as the remote one, thus making up a &amp;#8220;staging&amp;#8221; area. So, make a change to your local repository. I just make a new file on my linux distro. Then check the status of your repository using the &lt;code&gt;git status&lt;/code&gt; command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  $ touch newfile $ git status
  # On branch master
  #
  # Initial commit
  #
  # Untracked files:
  #   (use &amp;quot;git add &amp;lt;file&amp;gt;...&amp;quot; to include in what will be committed)
  #
  # newfile nothing added to commit but untracked files present (use &amp;quot;git
    add&amp;quot; to track)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see that the file &lt;code&gt;newfile&lt;/code&gt; shows up in &lt;em&gt;Untracked files&lt;/em&gt; (also notice that it is on branch master and it&amp;#8217;s called the &amp;#8220;Initial commit&amp;#8221;). This means that &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; will not look for changes in these files and not care about them. &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; also tells you how to add them. So :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ git add newfile $ git status
# On branch master
#
# Initial commit
#
# Changes to be committed:
#   (use &amp;quot;git rm --cached &amp;lt;file&amp;gt;...&amp;quot; to unstage)
#
# new file:   newfile
#&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now there are not untracked changes and &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; tells you how to unstage the changes you have made. It also defines what kind of changes it is with the &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;new file:&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; tag. This could be &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;modified&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; if this was not a new file but a modification. Now to the serious stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='committing_changes'&gt;Committing Changes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Committing is the mechanism by which you save some changes to the repo. A &amp;#8220;commit&amp;#8221; is essentially a snapshot of the repo at some point in time. You can use these to revert back to a state that you want to be if, for instance, you made a mistake somewhere. Commits are identified in &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; by messages and hashes. We have the one change we can commit. So here goes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ git commit -m &amp;quot;Initial commit&amp;quot; 
[master (root-commit) a2cdecf] Initalcommit 
0 files changed create mode 100644 newfile&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice I use the &lt;code&gt;-m&lt;/code&gt; argument. This is the commit message (thus the m). If you don&amp;#8217;t provide this argument, &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; will open up the default system editor where you can put in the message. Generally, I find it easier to just type it out on the console. You must provide a message. &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; aborts the commit if no message if provided. Now your local repo has a commit, if you want to look at the history you can use the &lt;code&gt;git log&lt;/code&gt; command. Now make a change to the file and see what happens when you do &lt;code&gt;git status&lt;/code&gt;. Finally, this is all fine but all this is still on your machine. How can we get this up to the server? That is where the &amp;#8220;push&amp;#8221; command comes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='pushing_commits'&gt;Pushing commits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this should be easy now. You have already set up a remote server at &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;origin&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;. However, you need to link up your local brances with the remote server stuff. Simply use the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ git push origin master&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, you don&amp;#8217;t want to be doing that everytime. You can do something like this for the first commit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ git push -u origin --all&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this does is, it takes all you local brances and maps them to the same names on the remote &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; server at &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;origin&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; and also sets the &amp;#8220;upstream&amp;#8221; of you local repo to &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;origin&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;. So all you have to do from now onwards is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ git push 
Counting objects: 3, done. 
Writing objects: 100% (3/3), 207 bytes, done. 
Total 3 (delta 0), reused 0 (delta 0) To ssh://git@bitbucket.org/saadfarooq/test.git
* [new branch]      master -&amp;gt; master&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it will know the repo and branch to push your commits to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='cloning'&gt;Cloning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cloning is a way to get a copy of a remote repo on to your local machine. The command is pretty simple and most sites provide you with the entire command when you go to the repos page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  $ git clone &amp;lt;repository url&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you do a clone, it connects all the local and remote branches automatically. One of the reasons I bring this in late is because that is how I started with &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; and I find that you don&amp;#8217;t end up learning enough about the workings of the system if you do it this way and it therefore takes you longer to build expertise with the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id='coming_soon'&gt;Coming soon&amp;#8230;.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;ll look at getting other peoples commits from the remote repo on to your local machine so we can start using this for collaborating on code instead of just backing up stuff.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>